<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Lia.Skalkos]]></title>
  <link href="http://lskalkos.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lskalkos.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-16T12:24:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://lskalkos.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Lia Skalkos]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Programming Makes You a Better Person]]></title>
    <link href="http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/08/16/how-programming-makes-you-a-better-person/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-16T14:00:40-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/08/16/how-programming-makes-you-a-better-person</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  People think that computer science is the art of geniuses but the actual reality is the opposite, just many people doing things that build on each other, like a wall of mini stones.
  <br>
  <br>
  Donald Knuth
</blockquote>




<ul>
  <li><strong>It's humbling</strong></li>
  <p>You get to work with really smart people. Also, if you haven't followed the traditional route of getting a computer science degree, you learn how to deal with facing higher barriers of entry to the field. You learn to deal with the fact that some people are just going to be more competitive candidates than you, and that all you can do is strive to be better.</p>
  <li><strong>It's also empowering</strong></li>
  <p>While there are differences in people's ability, you realize that you have more or less potential as anyone else to contribute positively to the world. Programming solves problems.</p>
  <li><strong>You begin to question things at a deeper level.</strong></li>
  <p>Programming is effective at eliminating assumptions about the way something works. You become better at evaluating your own false preconceptions, often of which, to your surprise, there are many. This way of thinking inevitably expands into other areas of your life. You become slower to jump to conclusions. You begin to question what you're told, and learn that you need to find out for yourself. As a result, you become more effective in your work and life, and you tend to trust yourself more. You have fewer opinions and tend to value evidence-based approaches. This begins to apply on a wider and wider scale.</p>
  <li><strong>It encourages you to be a team player</strong></li>
  <p>Sometimes you have to put aside your own thinking for the team, which ultimately is linked to the goal of the project itself. You discover that you can accomplish more through working with others.</p>
  <li><strong>It encourages you to be analytical</strong></li>
  <p>The more understanding you have of something, the easier is becomes to solve a problem related to it. You think about the reasoning behind a certain approach.</p>
  <li><strong>You can actually contribute to the body of human knowledge</strong></li>
  <p>While human advancement has often been portrayed as the lone genius having a stroke of insight, the reality is that progress is built on the groundwork of others. Other more academic fields such as physics or biology have a high bar of entry -- you have to have been studying them long enough to contribute to a niche area. With programming it's fairly easy to add to the common body of knowledge.</p>
  <li><strong>It rewards persistance, resourcefulness, and hard work</strong></li>
  <p>You often come across problems for which you can't find solutions on the internet and have to come up with it yourself.</p>
  <li><strong>It gives you a renewed appreciation for education</strong></li>
  <p>When you've had to slog through hours of debugging or learning to code on your own, you gain such an appreciation for someone telling you how to something. Then you suck the information so hard from their brain that they never have to tell you again, and now you are a 10X more efficient programmer. It makes you understand the value of education, which is to enable you to think critically and solve problems. As a consequence, it makes you want to help educate others.</p>
  <li><strong>It rewards curiosity and a love for learning</strong></li>
  <p>It's a privelege to be able to do something that is intellectually challenging, where you get to learn something new everyday.</p>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TDD vs. BDD vs. Unit vs. Functional Testing and More]]></title>
    <link href="http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/08/02/tdd-vs-bdd-vs-units-vs-functional-testing/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-02T12:56:49-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/08/02/tdd-vs-bdd-vs-units-vs-functional-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here at FlatIron we are about to embark on a TDD, or Test-Driven Development 2-week project sprint. With that in mind, I set out to learn more about testing, which is one of the most important part of building any application, and which I intend to learn a lot about. As I learned from listening to RailsConf, testing is more than making sure your application works as you expect &ndash; it also functions as a consistent form of communication across a team and application &ndash; meaning another developer can come on board, get oriented, and confidently begin contributing to an application with the tests as a guide. More than that, it can help communicate from the business requirement level to the development level. Soon after embarking on my test research mission, I found myself thrust into a complex world with terms like BDD (Behavior Driven Development), unit testing, functional testing, feature testing, and more. Since my team and I intend to take testing very seriously in this sprint, I thought I&rsquo;d take some time to explore each of these testing philosophies and see what they might contribute.</p>

<h2>Testing Paradigms/Processes</h2>


<p><strong>TDD / Test-Driven Development</strong></p>

<p>Test Driven Development refers to a process by which you develop and test your code. Under a TDD paradigm, your development process looks something like this:</p>


<ol>
  <li>Before coding, you write a test</li>
  <li>Run the tests along with any other tests</li>
  <li>Write the minimum amount of code necessary to make the tests pass</li>
  <li>Refactor</li>
  <li>Repeat the process</li>
</ol>


<p>TDD is not to be confused with unit testing or any other <i>style</i> of testing. Rather it refers to a process by which you can approach development. With TDD, you can get broad test coverage of your application. This gives you the confidence to make changes to your application as it grows, because you can see older tests passing and trust that your changes have not broken anything.</p>


<p><strong>BDD / Behavior-Driven Development</strong></p>

<p>Like TDD, Behavior Driven Development is a process by which you can approach development and testing. However, unlike TDD, BDD is more focused on <i>how</i> you test than <i>when</i> you test. With BDD, you focus your tests on behavior, rather than implementation, ideally starting from your customer's/user's expected experience. You picture your application as a black box (in other words, you try not to think about how your app reaches a result, but rather what the result should be first), from which the user gives an input, and they receive the expected result -- i.e. if I click on this button, I expect to see this result. This format leads to what is called <strong>outside-in testing</strong>, in which you begin with a high level test that begins with the user's expectation, and that test inevitably (and rather gracefully) drives you down to develop and test lower levels of your stack.</p>


<p>Perhaps the biggest contribution of BDD is that helps you avoid brittle testing and therefore a brittle design in your application. You can imagine that, if you start testing implementation rather than behavior, you may starts writing code that simply confirms the work you have already done. Starting with the highest level of functionality and letting that drive how you test and develop your application makes your code more flexible and resilient. For optimal development practice, BDD can and should be paired with TDD.</p>




<h2>Testing Types</h2>


<p><strong>Unit Test</strong></p>

<p>So what then is a unit test and how does it fit in to TDD/BDD? A unit test focuses on a single “unit of code”, such as a class method. Ideally the unit test in isolation from other dependencies, such as a connection to a database. All values should be stubbed or mocked, and the unit test runs solely in memory. That way you have a more abstract and thus more powerful low level test.</p>


<p><strong>Integration Test</strong></p>

<p>Per the name, an integration test builds on the unit test by testing multiple pieces of your application together. For example, testing an API interaction in your application. This type of test should find bugs that the unit test can't.</p>


<p><strong>Acceptance/Functional Tests</strong></p>

<p>Functional tests compare the result of a given input to a specification. These seem to be the most BDD-type of test, and they might be the best place to begin when designing your application. </p>




<p>The definition I read of acceptance test that I like best is "An acceptance test suite is basically an executable specification written in a domain specific language that describes the tests in the language used by the users of the system." Acceptance tests seem to be the test translation of the user specifications, and they test the functionality of the whole application at the highest level.</p>




<p>Obviously, there is no exact prescription for how to test an application. If you explore the interwebs, you'll find some surprisingly furious debate about the definition and purpose of all these different testing methodologies. But having even a general understanding of the different tools at your disposal should help you make better decisions for your application. All of these testing paradigms and types should be taken into consideration when building a robust test suite for your application that helps you design it better. If you're finding it difficult to write a test, take a moment and consider whether you're writing the right kind of to test. If you're starting at the unit test level, you may be starting too far down the stack. Figure out what your features are and work down. It might be difficult, but your application will be better as a result of it.</p>


<p>Sources:
<br>
<a href="https://robots.thoughtbot.com/testing-from-the-outsidein"><a href="https://robots.thoughtbot.com/testing-from-the-outsidein">https://robots.thoughtbot.com/testing-from-the-outsidein</a></a>
<br>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SOi_1reKn8M"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SOi_1reKn8M">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SOi_1reKn8M</a></a>
<br>
<a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4904096/whats-the-difference-between-unit-functional-acceptance-and-integration-test"><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4904096/whats-the-difference-between-unit-functional-acceptance-and-integration-test">http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4904096/whats-the-difference-between-unit-functional-acceptance-and-integration-test</a></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Javascript Is Interpreted]]></title>
    <link href="http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/07/19/how-javascript-is-interpreted/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-19T14:50:51-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/07/19/how-javascript-is-interpreted</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you work with Javascript you learn that, unlike Ruby, a function in JS can &ldquo;see&rdquo; and alter variables declared outside its scope. This is because of how scoping works in Javascript. An inner function could overwrite a variable declared in the outside scope, or you could redclare a local variable to give it new meaning. Seems pretty straightforward. Then I read this piece of code:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/349dcf53f89c9cf1cc5d.js?file=foo.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>var foo = 1;
function bar() {
    if (!foo) {
        var foo = 10;
    }
    console.log(foo);
}
bar();</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>Looking at this I thought, oh, well, the variable foo is defined in the main scope, so the if block inside the function bar() will never execute when bar() is called, since bar is able to read a from the main scope. Therefore the program writes 1 to the console.</p>

<p>Except no, it does not. It definitely writes 10 to the console. What the &amp;%$#^?</p>

<p>Here is another JS mind twister.</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/ccaefd5bece64f8531a4.js?file=b.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>var a = 1;
function b() {
    a = 10;
    return;
    function a() {}
}
b();
console.log(a);</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>Now 10 should definitely log to the console, right? Nope, it&rsquo;s 1. So what is going on?</p>

<p>This is where it turns out to be important to have some idea of how Javascript&rsquo;s interpreter works, and how scoping, variable definition, and function declaration/expression all come into play. It&rsquo;s kind of nonintuitive and more intertwined than I realized.</p>

<p>The question comes down to this: how do names actually come into scope in Javascript? It turns out it&rsquo;s through a well-defined order:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <strong>Language-defined</strong>
    <p>First, JS will apply language defined names to the scope. For example, all scopes within Javascript have the keywords <i>this</i>. Note that only functions create scope within Javascript. Thus, if you call a function within different functional contexts, the meaning of 'this' will change.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Formal parameters</strong>
    <p>Functions can have parameters formally defined on them. JS will read these next.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Function declarations</strong>
    <p>A function declaration looks like this:</p>
    <code>
      Declared(); //This will work as long as the function definition is declared in scope
      <br>
      function Declared(){
        //Some stuff here;
      }
    </code>
    <p>Declaration are "hoisted" to the top of the scope, so that you can effective call the function from anywhere within a function.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Variable declarations*</strong>
    <p>Note that these are the last thing to be defined by the interpreter, and the <i>assignment</i> is then *hoisted. <strong>However,</strong> the assignment still happens at the line of code where you declared it. This variable declaration rule also applies to function expressions (as opposed to function declarations, as in above).
    <br>
    <code>
      a(); //This will result in an error because the variable hasn't been assigned yet
      <br>
      var a = function() { //Some stuff here. };
    </code>
    </p>
  </li>
</ol>




<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/6393adc5f8af9f659e89.js?file=order_interpretation.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>//1. Language-defined

console.log(this); //This will print stuff out
function languageKeywordsDefinedFirst(){
    console.log(this); //This will also print stuff out
}

//2. Formal parameters

function parametersDefinedNext(name) {
    //First this/other language keywords defined
    //Then parameters like name
    console.log(name);
}

//3. Function declarations

function funcDeclarationsNext(string) {
    //First this/other language keywords defined
    //Then parameters like string
    //Then function declarations like aFuncDeclaration
    function aFuncDeclaration(){
        console.log(&quot;I&#39;m after language keywords and parameters&quot;);
    }
    
}

//4. Variable declarations

var a = 1;

function variablesLast(name){
    //First language keywords
    //Then parameters like name
    //Then function declarations like aDeclaration
    //Then variable declarations...which are hoisted!!
    var b = 2;
    function aDeclaration(){
        
    }
}</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p><caption>An overview of the order in which Javascript interprets code.</caption></p>

<p>With our new found knowledge we can then explain how our gnarly original Javascript brain teasers are working:</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/afb54acd52d366a807e4.js?file=foo_solution.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>var foo = 1;
function bar() {
  //var foo; --&gt; JS sees a local variable declaration of var foo within the function bar()
  //At this point foo is undefined
    if (!foo) {
        var foo = 10; //Thus, this line of code executes
    }
    console.log(foo); //foo is not equal to 10, and so 10 is logged to the console
}
bar(); //This prints 10</code></pre></noscript></div>




<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/c23bd7485d91eb08a820.js?file=b_solution.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>var a = 1;
function b() {
  //var a; --&gt; JS sees a local variable declaration of var a due to the function expression on line 6
    a = 10; //Thus, the function b() assigns the local variable a to 10....and not the outer variable a.
    return;
    function a() {}
}
b();
console.log(a); //This statement reads from the outer variable a, which remains 1. Thus it prints 1.</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>Sources:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.adequatelygood.com/JavaScript-Scoping-and-Hoisting.html"><a href="http://www.adequatelygood.com/JavaScript-Scoping-and-Hoisting.html">http://www.adequatelygood.com/JavaScript-Scoping-and-Hoisting.html</a></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minority Report:<br />Ruby Exceptions & Errors]]></title>
    <link href="http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/06/28/minority-report-exception-handling-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-28T16:25:01-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/06/28/minority-report-exception-handling-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not too long ago in one of our labs at Flatiron, we were asked to write some code that made this test pass:<br><br>
<code>
  it &ldquo;should raise an error for invalid types&rdquo; do
  expect { RPSGame.new(:dynamite) }.to raise_error(RPSGame::PlayTypeError)
  end<br/>
</code></p>

<p>After puzzling over this for a little, and reading some documentation, I got the test to pass by writing the following code:</p>

<p><code>
  class RPSGame
    attr_reader :type</p>

<pre><code>class PlayTypeError &lt; StandardError
end

def self.valid_types
  @@valid_types = [:rock, :paper, :scissors]
end

def initialize(type)
  @type = type
  raise(PlayTypeError.new) if !self.class.valid_types.include?(@type)
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end<br/>
</code></p>

<p>What was this neat little piece of code doing? Basically, raising an error if the user tried to enter an invalid action. I thought it was interesting, but soon moved on to other parts of the lab. However, I never forgot about the interesting little piece of code I had encountered. Ruby exceptions still feel inherently different to me than other parts of the language. They seem to be a little exotic, like rare birds in forest full of, I don&rsquo;t know, carrier pigeons. I guess this feeling makes sense, since exceptions tend to only come into play when things in our program go wrong. Also, there are a couple of special methods associated with them that not every class of object has. So, with that little intro here are 7 things that are helpful in understanding exceptions:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <strong>First and foremost, exceptions are Ruby objects.</strong>
    <p>Like nearly everything in Ruby, exceptions are objects. This is great in that they can contain information about themselves, and can have a real presence within our programs. They can be passed around and instantiated whenever necessary.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Exceptions are for exceptional circumstances.</strong>
    <p>You probably don't want to use an exception in place of a well thought-out program and appropriate logic constraints. Say, in an application that already has built-in form/params logic, trying to guide the user towards a different input type. Instead, you probably want to make use of exceptions where it's reasonable that an unlikely but highly detrimental situation to your program could occur. It's nice here to spend some time thinking about what kind of tool exceptions are and where they would work best.</p>
    <p>Imagine we have an app that uses a 3rd party API. What happens if the connection times out, or the 3rd party's server is down, or for whatever other reason, their DNS isn't working? It's unlikely to happen, but because our application has this dependency, it's reasonable to have a contingency plan. This use case is a good example of where exceptions make a good fit. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Exceptions can be raised.</strong>
    <p>
      The raise method is from the Kernel module. By default, raise will create an exception of the RuntimeError class. To raise an exception of a specific class, you can pass in the class name as an argument.<br><br>
      <code>
        raise "Here is a regular RuntimeError"<br>
        raise StandardError.new("Here is a StandardError")
      </code>
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>When an exception is raised, it halts the program.</strong>
    <p>
      As a Ruby programmer, you encounter this on a day-to-day basis. Here's an example:<br>
      <code>
        "10" + 3<br>
        TypeError: no implicit conversion of Fixnum into String
      </code>
      There's no way to continue from here. Basically, this is where our program has ended up.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Exceptions are associated with begin/rescue blocks.</strong>
    <p>Begin/rescue blocks function a lot like if statements, in that if an exception is thrown in the "begin" part, you can rescue from it and essentially branch your program. Unlike an if statement, however, they can be a little more granular about what type of exception to rescue from.
      <div><script src='https://gist.github.com/28839b613ab07b5494db.js?file=gistfile1.rb'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>a = 7
b = &quot;10&quot;

begin
   a + b #executes the expression
rescue
   puts &quot;Could not add variables a (#{a.class}) and b (#{b.class})&quot; #if an an exception is raised, this part will fire
else
   puts &quot;a + b is #{a + b}&quot; #otherwise, this part will fire 
end</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Exceptions have methods.</strong>
    <p>This ties into #1. They basically are backtrace, message, and inspect.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Make sure you specify the Exception type you are rescuing from.</strong>
    <p>
      Probably the most important point for last. Errors inherit from the class Exception.<br>
      <div><script src='https://gist.github.com/a6a37e11d8ae1d57d51e.js?file=exception_family_tree'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>Exception
 NoMemoryError
 ScriptError
   LoadError
   NotImplementedError
   SyntaxError
 SignalException
   Interrupt
 StandardError
   ArgumentError
   IOError
     EOFError
   IndexError
   LocalJumpError
   NameError
     NoMethodError
   RangeError
     FloatDomainError
   RegexpError
   RuntimeError
   SecurityError
   SystemCallError
   SystemStackError
   ThreadError
   TypeError
   ZeroDivisionError
 SystemExit
 fatal</code></pre></noscript></div>
<br>
      As you can see, Exception has a big family tree. When you rescue from an Exception, you want to be as specific as possible about the type, so that you don't accidentally rescue from an exception you weren't anticipating.
      <div><script src='https://gist.github.com/a5f470a80d8df4c2d1d9.js?file=rescuing.rb'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>
#This code will rescue from ANY type of exception (like a SyntaxError)!! 
begin
  some_method
rescue Exception =&gt; e
  do_some_rescue_stuff_and_examine_this_exception
end

#This code will rescue from StandardErrors. Better!!
begin
  some_method
rescue =&gt; e
  do_some_rescue_stuff_and_examine_this_exception
end

#This code will rescue from PlayTypeErrors, which we have defined ourselves.
begin
  some_method
rescue PlayTypeError =&gt; e
  do_some_rescue_stuff_and_examine_this_exception
end

</code></pre></noscript></div>
<br>
      This wouldn't be fun, if say, you were trying to rescure from a connection error, and instead rescued from a NoMethodError. You have then unintentionally branched your program into the wrong type of logic.
    </p>
  </li>
</ol>


<p>Sources:<br>
<a href="http://daniel.fone.net.nz/blog/2013/05/28/why-you-should-never-rescue-exception-in-ruby/"><a href="http://daniel.fone.net.nz/blog/2013/05/28/why-you-should-never-rescue-exception-in-ruby/">http://daniel.fone.net.nz/blog/2013/05/28/why-you-should-never-rescue-exception-in-ruby/</a></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Efficient Coding With Rubymine:<br />a Quick Guide]]></title>
    <link href="http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/06/20/efficient-coding-with-rubymine/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-20T11:04:32-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/06/20/efficient-coding-with-rubymine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Programmers tend to be a crew that likes their tools. From the OS, to version control, to bash and Ruby itself, one could argue that pretty much every aspect of programming involves a tool. Usually, the linchpin of all these tools is the text editor, the place where the code actually gets written. Recently, instead of using Sublime Text, I&rsquo;ve been using an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integrated_development_environment">IDE</a> called Rubymine. While I&rsquo;m a fan of Sublime Text, I&rsquo;ve been finding that Rubymine provides some advantages that give me a boost in efficiency. In this post I give a quick review of some of Rubymine&rsquo;s features.</p>

<h3>Debugging</h3>


<p>Rubymine comes with a built in visual debugger that can function as an alternative to debugging with pry. Let&rsquo;s take a look at how this works.</p>

<p>Navigate over to the rspec test you want to run (or the file that serves as your program&rsquo;s entry point), right click, and select debug (or Option + Shift + D). You can also select a specific test to run within a spec. If there are no bugs, your test will pass and your program will run. When you debug, three tabs will open up at the bottom: the Debugger, Console, and Interactive Console. The Console reports the output of your test, and will alert you if there are any errors. Let&rsquo;s say you run a test and you hit an error. Here are the steps you can take to take advantage of Rubymine&rsquo;s debugging capabilities:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Head over to the line in your program where Ruby ran into a problem.</p></li>
<li><p>Set a &ldquo;breakpoint&rdquo; &ndash; this is very similar to setting a binding.pry. The next time your program runs Rubymine will stop it at this point. Use Command + fn + F8 to set a breakpoint. You can set several of these at a time. <img src="images/rubymine_breakpoint.png" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto 20px;"/></p></li>
<li><p>Rerun your debugger (Option + Shift + D).</p></li>
<li><p>Now, when you check the debugger tab you&rsquo;ll be shown the current values of the local variables within the scope of your breakpoint <em>and</em> Rubymine will write out these values in your actual code. You can also get access to an Expression Evaluator and can set a watch or a condition on variables or expresssions to see how they change as you move through your code. <img src="images/rubymine_local_variables.png" style="displauy: block; margin: 20px auto 20px;"/></p></li>
<li><p>Head over to the Interactive Console for an IRB that gives you access to these variables.</p></li>
<li><p>Once you&rsquo;ve corrected your code, hit &lsquo;Rerun&rsquo; to rerun your test.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>This might not sound like it&rsquo;s that different from using pry, but when you&rsquo;re debugging, getting visual cues and having all of the information in one place without having to run multiple commands and switch between panels seems invaluable.</p>

<h3>Syntax Highlighting & Auto Suggestion</h3>


<p>Rubymine remembers your classes and their methods no matter where you are in your program, so when you reference a class or create a new instance it provides a list of method suggestions. Pretty helpful when you&rsquo;re trying to remember a method. Also, unlike Sublime Text, it provides code completion and signals you when you have a syntax error or have misused a local variable. No more having to type &ldquo;end&rdquo; to a if block.</p>

<p><img src="images/rubymine_autosuggest.png" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto 20px;"/></p>

<h3>Terminal</h3>


<p></p>

<p>You can run bash directly from Rubymine. Need I say more? No more need to shift + tab back and forth from terminal.</p>

<p>The Verdict?</p>

<p>Rubymine seems to be super powerful. It has other features which I haven&rsquo;t begun to explore, like other language and refactoring support. It&rsquo;s keyboard-centric, which means it&rsquo;s meant to be handled through keyboard commands as much as possible. Of course, having to learn a bunch of keyboard commands can be time-consuming and an extra stress when you&rsquo;re already trying to learn something new. But, once you have a good number down, they save you a lot of time. Rubymine definitely takes more time to learn than Sublime Text, and can be a learning project all on its own. There are a ton of features, which can seem overwhelming and like a distraction from the actual task: coding. Also, at $99 for an individual license, it&rsquo;s not cheap. But an upfront investment of time and money seems very likely to payoff in terms of efficiency and support.</p>

<p>Some purists might argue that they like sparse tools like Vim better because they can code right from the command line. In my view, why not use a tool that can provide you more context immediately? When you&rsquo;re doing something as cognitively involved as coding, it helps to have all the signaling you can get.</p>

<p>In the end, there is no &ldquo;best&rdquo; text editor or environment set up &ndash; it&rsquo;s a matter of individual taste and circumstance and what you feel supports you best in your workflow. As long as a tool is empowering you, it&rsquo;s worthwhile. I&rsquo;m still getting to know Rubymine, but for now, I&rsquo;m enjoying it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zen and the Art of Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/06/09/zen-and-the-art-of-programming/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-09T17:21:57-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://lskalkos.github.io/blog/2015/06/09/zen-and-the-art-of-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Practice makes the master.</em> -Spanish saying</p>

<p>Some time ago, I was applying for a developer job at a startup. Part of the application process involved solving a code challenge that required you to programmatically retrieve and manipulate a set of data through an API. I chose to do the challenge in Node.js, because I like Node (and Javascript-y things in general) and because Node was a key part of the company&rsquo;s product and of the job I was applying for.</p>

<p>I remember firing up Sublime, writing some preliminary code, and retrieving the first set of data. I felt great. I felt like, &ldquo;I got this&rdquo;. In fact, I had a lot of big feelings about this one code challenge. Up until that point, I was largely a self-taught developer. I thought, how amazing would it be if I got this job, having learned to code mostly on my own. Like, it would be mean I Am Really Smart after all and Totally A Real Developer and all these other big things that would validate me and free me from my insecurities. Then I got deeper into the problem.</p>

<p>Long story short, I hit a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree_(data_structure)">nested tree-like structure</a> part of the problem. I tried recursion, but that seemed to be a friggin nightmare. Then a colleague suggested I try a queue instead of recursion. That seemed to be better, but I was still in <a href="http://callbackhell.com">callback hell</a> thanks to Javascript&rsquo;s lovely <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/apps/hh700330.aspx">asynchronous nature</a>.</p>

<p>The details of the problem are largely unimportant. What <em>is</em> important is that I spent a weekend on the problem. Actually, more than a weekend on it. From the time I received the challenge, I spent literally every waking second on it, well into the week, well into when I should not have been thinking about it anymore, like when I should have been eating or taking bathroom breaks or sleeping. I was totally out of my element, and that was incredibly hard to accept. For most of that week, I couldn&rsquo;t even understand what my problem was, let alone how to fix it. It took me half the week alone to learn about tree structures &ndash; a way for me to conceptualize the problem &ndash; and even more days for me to learn about callback hell, and about Javascript&rsquo;s asynchronous nature.</p>

<p>The important thing about the problem was not that I solved it, but that I couldn&rsquo;t solve it, no matter how hard I tried, no matter how much I wanted it. It was torture. Just like I had felt solving the problem would say something great about me, not solving the problem seemed to say something awful about me.</p>

<p>So much in life is actually pretty easy. You show up, you do the work, you get the credit. Actually, most things in life are pretty effortless. And so even when we know we have to put in the time to learn something, or to solve something, we still expect that process to be effortless. Like a savings account, we expect to put some time in and get a reliable return.</p>

<p>But sometimes things are beyond our control. Sometimes you can&rsquo;t solve that problem, at least, not right now, perhaps in this place, not in this way, or with this tool. I couldn&rsquo;t solve the problem on my own through the sheer force of my intellect. I researched it, wrestled with it, and yet I still didn&rsquo;t &ldquo;win&rdquo; &ndash; though what exactly I was trying to win remains a mystery.</p>

<p>Here is the paradox: we can&rsquo;t fully believe in our own mastery if it has been effortless. Problems in programming, as in life, require patience and faith &ndash; the faith that they will be resolved in time, though perhaps not in the way you would like, and the patience to struggle for awhile, though it may be uncomfortable for much longer than you anticipate. It is here where I like the Zen concept of beginner mind. No matter how experienced we are, if we always think of ourselves as a beginner, we can approach a problem with humility, openness, and a certain amount of self-gentleness. We can accept our frustration simply as evidence that we care deeply about our craft, and that we want it to be worth the struggle. In the words of one of my former coworkers, &ldquo;All is practice.&rdquo; If we are always practicing, then we are always learning. If we are always learning, then we have never fully arrived, and that&rsquo;s okay, because that was never really the point anyway. Mastery is not a binary state but a gradual unfolding, revealing itself to you when you least expect it.</p>

<p>The truth was this: my experience on this particular problem didn&rsquo;t say anything about me beyond the fact that I struggled with it for a while. It was just a moment in time.</p>

<p>In the end, I did end up submitting a beautiful little program with the help of my colleague and <a href="https://www.promisejs.org">Promises.js</a>. It worked, and while I didn&rsquo;t end up working for the company, I gained so much more by pushing myself farther beyond where I possibly thought I could go.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
